The Life of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 1
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراَّ
Rasool Allah ﷺ sends Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) and Zaid Bin Harissa (زيد بن حارثه)
to deliver the news to the people of Madina.
Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) goes to Awali(عوالي), the upper areas of Madina
and he delivers the news to each house of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار),
while Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) goes to the center of Madina to deliver the news.
Now Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) was riding on the camel of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, when he came in, delivering the news and saying that
Ut'bah Bin Rabiyah(عتبة بن ربيعة) was killed,
Shaibah Bin Rabiyah(شيبة بن ربيعة) was killed
Ibn Al-Hajjaj(إبن الحجاج) were killed,
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) was killed
and he was mentioning the famous names of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), who were killed.
The Munafiqeen(منافقين) and the Yahood(يهود) said;
This man doesn't know what he's talking about, he's confused
and he has run away from the battlefield,
and Muhammad(محمد) himself was killed
and the evidence is that Zaid(زيد) is riding his camel.
And they went around spreading this news.
So, Usamah(اسامه) said: I went to my father's Zaid(زيد)
because Usamah(اسامه) was left behind, he stayed in Madina to care for Ruqayyah(رقية).
Usamah(اسامه) and Uthman(عثمان) stayed behind to care for Ruqayyah(رقية) the daughter of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Usamah(اسامه) said;
I went to my father and said; O, Father is the news that you're delivering, true.?
He said, Yes, my son it is true.
People were going to Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) and saying is that news true?
He would say; yes, the news is true
and tomorrow Rasool Allah ﷺ is going to bring the captives.
It was so difficult for people to believe what happened,
a force of little over 300 defeats a 1000
and then kills the most famous names of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), all of them are dead
Ut'bah(عتبة), Shaibah(شيبة), Al-Waleed(الوليد), Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل),
Nabeeha Al-Munabbah(نبيحه ألمنبه), Ibn Al-Hajjaj(إبن ألحجاج) and others,
all of them were killed on that day.
And then other leaders, such as Sohail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو), are captured, taken as prisoners.
So, it was too good to be true,
but the next day, Rasool Allah ﷺ does come in with the prisoners and the victory of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Now, the prisoners were placed in a certain location
and Sodah(سؤده), the wife of Rasool Allah ﷺ
when she saw Sohail Bin Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) with his hands tied to his neck.
And this was one of the noblemen of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
She said: Why didn't you die as nobleman?
Why did you allow yourselves to be humiliated and to be in this state?
Why didn't you, die as nobleman.
اَفَلَا اَمِتُّمْ كِرَامًا
Rasool Allah ﷺ overlooked that statement and said;
اَعَلَی لَّلّهُ وَرَسُوْلِهِ تُحَّرِّضِيِنْ
Are you asking them to fight Allah and His Messenger?
Because in fact, what she was saying is,
why didn't you fight rather than be held captive, the way you are,
and when she is saying why didn't he fight, who would he fight against.?
He would be fighting against Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Sodah(سؤده) said: She apologized, to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said,
O Messenger of Allah, When I saw him in that state,
I couldn't, but say such a statement.
Her emotions overwhelmed her, when she saw Sohail(سهيل) in that state.
So, it tells you that the leaders of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were humiliated because of their disbelief and Kuffr(كفر)
and the way they dealt with the Messenger of Allah ﷺ,
most of them were killed
and then you have the people like SohailIbn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) are tied in ropes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ stopped at Ar-Rohaa(ألروحاء) to receive congratulations, from all of the people that were coming to visit him.
And when the people were coming to congratulate him
one of the Ansaar(ألأنصار) said:
What are you congratulating us for,
We have only met old, bald men, like camels awaiting slaughter
and we slaughtered them.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said, Hey my cousin, Don't say that, these are the chiefs.
This Ansaari(اَنصاري) was saying it was so easy,
those people whom we faced are old men who don't know how to fight.
It was Allah who helped you, through the angels, otherwise we couldn't have defeated such an army.
So, these are strong men, it was a strong opponent,
but Allahعَزّوجَلّ assisted us, and helped us.
The news was delivered to Makkah by a man called Al-Haithamaan Al-Khuza'ee(ألحُيْسمان ألخزاعي)
Al-Haithamaan Al-Khuza'ee(ألحُيْسمان ألخزاعي) rushes into Makkah and says,
Abul Hakam(ابو الكحم) was killed,
Ut'ba(عتبة) was killed,
Shaibah(شيبة) was killed,
Al-Waleed(الوليد) was killed,
and he's going down the list,
and Ummayyah(اميه) was killed.
Safwaan Ibn Ummayyah(صفوان ابن اميه) was listening.
And he said: This man has lost his mind.
Ask him about me, to make sure that, he isn't crazy.
So, they asked him.
What about Safwaan(صفوان), what happened to him.?
He said; Safwaan(صفوان) is sitting right there.
And I have seen the death of his father and his brother with my own eyes.
And for the people of Makkah it was too bad to be true.
How could Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) be killed, and Ummayyah(اميه) be killed, and Ut'ba(عتبة) be killed?
It's impossible,
but surely the news was sinking in.
Abu Lahab(ابولهب) was one of those, who stayed behind,
but he sent somebody in his place to fight.
Raafiah(رافع) says that I was a servant of Al-Abbas(العباس)
and our household was Muslim, Me and Al-Abbas(العباس) and Ummul Fazal(أم الفضل),
Ummul Fazal(أم الفضل) is the wife ofAl-Abbas(العباس), we were Muslim.
And I used to make arrows.
So, I was sitting in the pavilion around the Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), sharpening arrows,
while Abu Lahab(ابولهب) was sitting with his back towards me,
when one of the fighters from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) approached.
So, Abu Lahab(ابولهب) said; Come and tell us the news of what happened?
So, the man came and he said;
As soon as the fighting started
we handed them over ourselves to be killed and to be taken as captives.
But I don't blame them for it,
because we were facing men in white clothes
on horses, between the heavens and earth, and nothing can stop them.
So, he was saying that it is true that we were defeated by the army of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
But we don't give credit to them.
It was some other people wearing white who defeated us and nothing could stop that force.
When Raafiah(رافع) heard that, he said, In the name of Allah, those are the angels.
Abu Lahab(ابولهب) turned around and punched him in the face, such a blow.
Raafiah(رافع) said: So, I started fighting back
but Abu Lahab(ابولهب) was stronger than me and I was a weak man
So, he was sitting over me and beating me hard,
when Ummul Fazal(أم الفضل) came with a rod and she hit Abu Lahab(ابولهب) on the head
and told him; You are taking advantage that his master is not around.
Then Abu Lahab(ابولهب) left.
Raafiah(رافع) says, that Abu Lahab(ابولهب) was afflicted by disease after that and died a week later.
And he said this particular disease would terrify the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And if somebody is inflicted with that disease, they wouldn't want to go next to him.
So, Abu Lahab(ابولهب) died and remained in his house for three days until, his body was decomposing,
and nobody wants to bury him.
So, The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) went to his two sons and said,
I mean, shame on you, your father, his body is decomposing, and you don't want to bury him.
They said, well, we're afraid of that disease.
So what they did is,
they ended up dragging him and placing him next to a wall.
They didn't even dig a grave for him, they placed him next to wall,
and then they threw stones over him to cover his body.
That is the humiliation that he suffered, even in his death.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) in order not to have the Muslims rejoice at their misfortune
prevented anyone from crying publicly for the dead.
So, there was no wailing allowed.
Also, they refused to allow anybody to investigate the issue of ransoming, the prisoners.
So that Muhammadﷺ will not raise the price of ransom.
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر), He says about this.
He said, I observe that Allah's forcing them to forego mourning for their dead
was part of the totality of His punishment, of those of them that remained alive at that time,
for weeping for the dead contributes to the recovery of the grieving heart.
So, this prevention of mourning was in fact more of a torment for the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
the ones who are living.
And then he says, Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) stated
Al-Aswad Ibn Al-Muttalib(ألأسود ابن المطلب) was afflicted with the loss of three of his sons.
This was an old man, he was already blind, and he lost three of his sons
and he wasn't allowed to mourn their deaths.
So, one night he hears a woman weeping.
So, he said; Go and see if mourning has become permissible
are Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) now be wailing their dead,
perhaps I will now be able to lament the loss of Abu Hakima(ابوحكيمه), his eldest son,
for I am in great pain.
So, they went to find out why the woman was crying?
They found out she's crying because he lost a camel.
So, he says these lines of poetry, he said,
Is she weeping because of a camel of hers has gone astray...
And so insomnia keeps her from sleeping...
Do not weep over young camel...
But over Badr(بدر) that ruined all hopes...
over Badr(بدر) and the elite of the Bannu Husais(بنو هصيص) and Makhzoom(مخذوم)...
And the tribe of Abul Waleed(أبو الوليد)...
And weep if you weep at all...
For Abu Aqeel(أبو عقيل)... And for Harris(حارث)...
The Lion of lions, Weep for them all and do not hold back...
For there is none, The like of Abu Hakeema(ابوحكيمة)...
after them it is other men who rule, and had it not been for Badr(بدر)...
They would not have come to lead...
So, this poor old man wasn't even allowed to mourn the loss of his three sons.
Why?
So, that the news wouldn't reach to Muhammadﷺ that the Kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are suffering
because of their dead, they wanted to show they don't care about it.
And they wanted to show that, they don't care about the ransom of the captives.
Surat-Al-Anfaal(سورة الأنفال) was revealed, after the Ghazwa(غزوة) of Badr(بدر).
Ubadah Bin Samit(عبادة بن الصامت) says about the first verses of Surat-Al-Anfaal(سورة الأنفال).
They were revealed about us, The Muslims at Badr(بدر).
When we disputed the issue of booty
وَسَاعَتْ فِيْ اَخْلَاقُنَا
and we were disputing with one another about it.
What happened was the Muslims were three groups one group was protecting Rasool Allah ﷺ,
the second group was pursuing the enemy
and the third group were collecting the spoils of war.
So, the ones who collected the spoils of war said, these belong to us.
The ones, who protected Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
No, we want our share because we are protecting Rasool Ullah.
And the ones who are pursuing the enemy said;
If it wasn't for us you wouldn't have any spoils of war.
So, they disputed and they were arguing
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayaat(آيات) of Surat-Al-Anfaal(سورة الأنفال).
يَسْأَلُونَكَ عَنِ الْأَنْفَالِ ۖ قُلِ الْأَنْفَالُ لِلَّهِ وَالرَّسُولِ ۖ
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says: They ask you, O Muhammad(محمد) about the bounties of war,
say the decision concerning bounties is for Allah and the Messenger.
Therefore all of the boundaries of war were taken from them, and given to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
It belongs to Allah and Rasool Ullah, all of it was taken away.
And then Allah says; So, fear Allah
and amend that which is between you and obey Allah and His Messenger, if you should be believers.
So, this Ayaah(آية) is teaching the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) that they should have Taqwa(تقوى),
you cannot fight Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) without Taqwa(تقوى).
Number two, and amend that which is between you and you have to have unity
for fighters Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), they have to be one.
And number three and obey Allah and His Messenger,
you have to have discipline
fighters without discipline are not going to succeed.
So, they have to have discipline and obedience of the leader.
So, these are three essential qualities for Al-Mujahideen(المجاهدين) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
Taqwa(تقوى) and unity, and discipline and obedience of the leader.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ gives the ruling regarding, how the spoils of war are divided?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَاعْلَمُوا أَنَّمَا غَنِمْتُمْ مِنْ شَيْءٍ فَأَنَّ لِلَّهِ خُمُسَهُ وَلِلرَّسُولِ
وَلِلرَّسُولِ وَلِذِي الْقُرْبَىٰ وَالْيَتَامَىٰ وَالْمَسَاكِينِ وَابْنِ السَّبِيلِ
إِنْ كُنْتُمْ آمَنْتُمْ بِاللَّهِ وَمَا أَنْزَلْنَا عَلَىٰ عَبْدِنَا يَوْمَ الْفُرْقَانِ
يَوْمَ الْفُرْقَانِ يَوْمَ الْتَقَى الْجَمْعَانِ ۗ
وَاللَّهُ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرٌ۝
And know that anything you obtain of war booty.
Indeed, for Allah is one fifth of it and for the messenger
and for his nearer relatives, and the orphans, the needy
and the stranded traveler.
If you have believed in Allah and in that which we sent down to our servant, on the day of criterion,
The day when the two armies met
and Allah over all things is competent.
So, the ruling regarding the spoils of war is as follows,
They are divided into five portions, five equal portions
four of those, five portions are distributed among the fighters.
So, 80% if we convert it to percentage,
80% of the spoils of war are split among the fighters.
The foot soldier receives one share
and the horsemen receive three shares, the cavalry three shares each.
The remaining 20% is then divided into five portions,
so we're talking about 4% each
4% goes to Allah,
4% goes to Rasool Ullah,
4% goes to the near relatives,
4% goes to the orphans,
4% goes to the poor
and 4% goes to the traveler.
Now the portion that goes to Allah and Rasool Allah ﷺ is distributed in what is needed by the Muslims,
such as Masajid(مساجد) or paving roads or whatever,
it is up to the Imam(إمام) of the Muslims to distribute that.
So, these are the rulings regarding the distribution of the booty.
Another issue dealt with in the Ayaat(آيات) of Surat-Al-Anfaal(سورة الأنفال),
the prisoners of war.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has 70 prisoners of war.
So, he invites the Sahabah for Shura(شورى),
and he hears various opinions.
Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه speaks, and his opinion was;
O Messenger of Allah, These are our relatives, these are our tribe ask for ransom.
This ransom will strengthen us, it will strengthen Islam
and maybe these people will become Muslim.
So, that was the opinion of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر).
He says; O, Messenger of Allah, they are your people, your relatives,
let them live, be lenient to them, perhaps Allah will forgive them.
Umar Bin Khattab(عمر بن خطاب) said;
O Messenger of Allah, they exiled you and called you a liar, bring them close and strike their necks.
This was the opinion of Umar(عُمَر).
In another narration, it says, Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) said;
O Messenger of Allah, these are your close relatives, your tribal brothers,
I think you should accept ransom from them,
what we receive from them will give us power against the unbelievers
and Allah might well give them guidance so that they become allied to us.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: I don't agree with Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
I think you should hand over to me so and so
referring to one of his relatives, and I'll strike his neck.
And you hand over Aqeel(عقيل) to his brother Ali(علي).
So, he can strike his neck
and you hand over to Hamza(حمزه) so and so, his brother, so he can strike his neck.
That way Allah will know that we feel no leniency towards the Mushrikeen(مشركين).
These men are their chieftains, their very leaders.
And in another narration Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة) spoke,
And he said, I suggest, O Messenger of Allah
you find the valley with many trees, make them enter it and then set them on fire.
You burn them in that valley, that was the opinion of Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ went in, and then it came out
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
Allah softens the hearts of men concerning Him
so that they become softer than soft,
and Allah hardens the hearts of men
so that they become harder than stone.
You Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) are like Ibrahim(ابراهيم) who said;
Whoever follows me, is of me
and whoever disobeys me then you are Forgiving and Merciful.
You Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) are like Jesus, who said;
If You punish them, they are Your servants.
If You forgive them, then You are the all powerful and Wise.
So, the analogy of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), he is similar to Ibrahim(ابراهيم) and Eesa(عيسى),
who were lenient, with their people.
You Umar(عُمَر) are like Noah(نوح), who said, O Lord,
Do not leave on the earth any place for the unbelievers.
Noah(نوح) made a Dua(دُعَا) to Allahعَزّوجَلّ to obliterate, to destroy all of the Kuffar(كفار).
And Umar you are like Musa(موسى), who said;
O Allah, destroy their wealth and make their hearts hard,
for they will not believe, until they see the painful punishment.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
Let none be exempt from either ransom or having their head smitten.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was inclined to adopt the opinion of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
and he was willing to accept ransom.
One Day, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) comes out and sees that Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) were crying.
Actually, the following day,
Umar(عُمَر) said;
I went to the Prophet ﷺ early in the morning
He was with Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) and they were weeping,
I asked: O, Messenger of Allah tell me, why you and your companion are weeping?
If I find the reason to weep, I'll do so, if I don't I'll pretend to weep at your weeping.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
I am weeping at how your companions proposed to me that I accept ransom.
Your punishment for doing so, was proposed to me,
and it was closer than this tree.
Meaning Allahعَزّوجَلّ wasn't happy that the Muslims accepted ransom.
Why.?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayaat(آيات) Sixty seven To 69 Surat-Al-Anfaal(سورة الأنفال)
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
مَا كَانَ لِنَبِيٍّ أَنْ يَكُونَ لَهُ أَسْرَىٰ حَتَّىٰ يُثْخِنَ فِي الْأَرْضِ ۚ
تُرِيدُونَ عَرَضَ الدُّنْيَا وَاللَّهُ يُرِيدُ الْآخِرَةَ ۗ وَاللَّهُ عَزِيزٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
لَوْلَا كِتَابٌ مِنَ اللَّهِ سَبَقَ لَمَسَّكُمْ فِيمَا أَخَذْتُمْ عَذَابٌ عَظِيمٌ۝
It is not for a Prophet to have captives of war,
until he inflicts a massacre upon Allah's enemies in the land.
You i.e. some Muslims desire the commodities of this world.
But Allah desires for you the hereafter and Allah is Exalted and Might and Wise.
If not for a decree from Allah that preceded,
you would have been touched for what you took by great punishment.
Two things in these Ayaat(آيات).
Number one;
Rasool Allah ﷺ should have executed them all.
That is what would have pleased Allahعَزّوجَلّ, to execute all of these prisoners.
Why.?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
It is not for Prophet to have captives of war, until he inflicts a slaughter upon Allah's enemies in the land.
A newly forming state, Jama'ah(جماعة) needs to show its strength in the beginning.
And asking for ransom here, is less of a strong opinion compared to the execution of all of those prisoners.
However, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in the following Ayaat(آيات) that
if it was not for a decree that proceeded from Allah you would have been touched by punishment.
Allah has made asking for ransom Halal(حلال)
And Allah has made Ghaneema(غنيمه) Halal(حلال).
Therefore what the Muslims did was allowed, otherwise they would have been punished.
So, I hope that this issue is clear.
Mujahid Ath-Thori(مجاهد ألثوري) say;
were it not for a decree from Allah that came previously that is in forgiving them,
while the majority opinion as Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) states
is that it is the allowing of Ghaneema(غنيمه) and ransom.
So what Rasool Allah ﷺ did was allowed.
However, it would have been better, if ransom was not accepted,
and these prisoners were executed.
Rasool Allah ﷺ as we mentioned, was employing the method of formal ranks in the battlefield,
rather than the method of the Arab warfare which was to attack and withdraw, in a not a very organized manner.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was straightening the lines,
as if he was straightening the lines for prayer.
And he was holding an arrow in his hand.
And he came up to one of the soldiers, Sawad Bin Ghuzaiyya(سوادبن غزية),
who was protruding a bit from the line.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ pushes him back with the arrow
sort of like with the arrow in his stomach, he pushes him back.
So, Sawad Bin Ghuzaiyya(سواد بن غزية) says,
O Rasool Ullah, You hurt me, I want to retaliate.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Sawad(سواد) this is right before the battle,
and you say to Rasool Allah ﷺ that I want to retaliate, just because he hurt you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, What was his response?
You know, here one of his soldier is saying that you hurt me, I want to retaliate now.
It's your mistake, Sawad(سواد), Why Weren't you standing straight in the line...
But Rasool Allah ﷺ exposed his stomach
and said go ahead and retaliate.
If that's what you want. Go ahead.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, did not get angry, he didn't get upset.
He didn't order his soldiers to take Sawad(سواد)
and court Marshal him, and throw him in jail, torture him
because he spoke insuch a fashion to the leader of the army, disobey the direct military order.
Rasool Allah ﷺ exposed his stomach and told him; Sawad(سواد) go ahead and retaliate.
If I hurt you, Go ahead and retaliate.
So, Sawad Bin Ghuzaiyya رضي الله عنه hugs Rasool Allah ﷺ and he kisses his stomach.
That was his retaliation.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Sawad:
مَا حَمَلَكَ عَلَى مَا صَنَعَتْ
Why did he do that?
Sawad Bin Ghuzaiyya(سواد بن غزية) said: O Messenger of Allah
You can see what is about to happen.
I wanted my last contact with you to be my skin touching yours.
لا اله الا الله
Sawad Bin Ghuzaiyya(سواد بن غزية) is saying;
O Messenger of Allah, you can see what is about to happen, I might die in a few moments in a few hours.
We're facing death right in front of us.
I wanted the last thing in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) to be, my skin touching yours.
This is how they loved Rasool Allah ﷺ
Sawad Bin Ghuzaiyya(سواد بن غزية), who was hurt by Rasool Allah ﷺ accidentally,
used this opportunity to kiss Rasool Allah ﷺ and to hug him.
They didn't see it, that Rasool Allah ﷺ was leading them to their death.
They didn't see it that they're suffering all of this troubled because of him and because of his Da'wah(دعوة).
They were willingly going ahead to face death, for the sake of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and His Servant and Messenger, Muhammadﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ then makes Dua(دُعَا) for Sawad(سواد), that may Allahعَزّوجَلّ bless him.
It is this love of Rasool Allah ﷺ that we want to learn from these series,
how the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم understood the meaning
and the concept of loving Muhammadﷺ,
what it meant to them, it wasn't just words on their tongues, poetry, singing his praise,
love for them meant that we'll put everything on the line for you.
Everything will lay it down for you, O Messenger of Allah, our wealth, our money, our family, our children.
Everything is sacrificeable when it comes to you, we're willing to give everything up.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to grant us this love of Muhammadﷺ,
the love of his message, the loveof his Sunnah, the love of his way.
And not just to make us people, who claim that they love him and pay it lip service.
And we asked Allahعَزّوجَلّ to make us love His Shariah(شريعه)
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in Qur'an,
And this something he granted the Shahabah
حَبَّبَ إِلَيْكُمُ الْإِيمَانَ وَزَيَّنَهُ فِي قُلُوبِكُمْ
He made you a love Eeman(ايمان) and made it adorned in your hearts.
So, for them Eeman(ايمان) was something that they loved.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says inthe Hadith(حديث),
you're not going to taste the sweetness of Eeman(إيمان), until one of three things.
One of them is that you would dislike going back to Kuffr(كفر) like you would dislike being thrown in fire.
So, you'd love Eeman(إيمان), so much that you would rather be thrown in fire to burn in fire, than to give it up.
You love your Eeman(إيمان), you love your Islam so much
that is when you would really taste the sweetness of Eeman(إيمان).
Rasool Allah ﷺ after he did his best in terms of preparation
in terms of arranging the army,
in terms of choosing the location
in terms of making Shura(شورى),
when he exhausted all of the worldly means, what did he do next?
The next thing he did, is put his trust in Allahعَزّوجَلّ and Make Dua(دُعَا).
Dear brothers and sisters, This is what Tawakkul(توكل) means,
it means that you do the best in terms of the worldly means, you exhaust them to the limit.
And then after that you throw the matter into the hands of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, you leave it to Him.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ now, after he did his best, he went a side, and he raised his hands.
And he started making Dua(دُعَا).
And he was so involved in that Dua(دُعَا).
And it took him so long, and he was saying, O Allah, I appeal to your pact and to your oath.
If you wish it, you will not be worshiped ever again, after this day.
Because this is it, these are the Muslims, if they're killed who will worship You.
And he went on and on making Dua(دُعَا) to Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) was feeling sorry for Muhammadﷺ,
he went to him and he said;
he held him by the hand and said;
that's enough O Messenger of Allah, it's enough of asking Your Lord.
Now the reason why Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) said that,
I'm quoting Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر)
he said, by saying these words, he was in a fact asking
Why are you so exhausting yourself?
Allah has made you a promise of help.
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), Allah bless him, was a tender hearted man, with great empathy, and compassion for the Messenger of Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, then went outside of his portico walking vigorously in his armor,
speaking the verse, the force will be defeated.
They will retreat, the hour will come and it will be most bitter.
سَيُهْزَمُ الْجَمْعُ وَيُوَلُّونَ الدُّبُرَ۝
بَلِالسَّاعَةُ مَوْعِدُهُمْ وَالسَّاعَةُ أَدْهَىٰ وَأَمَرُّ۝
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ has promised Rasool Allah ﷺ victory after his long Dua(دُعَا)
Allah (عَزّوجَلّ) says, in Surat-Al-Anfaal(سورة الأنفال)
إِذْ تَسْتَغِيثُونَ رَبَّكُمْ فَاسْتَجَابَ لَكُمْ أَنِّي مُمِدُّكُمْ بِأَلْفٍ مِنَ الْمَلَائِكَةِ مُرْدِفِينَ۝
Remember when you asked help of your Lord.
And He answered you indeed I will reinforce you with 1000 from the angels following one another.
So, this was the response that came back to Rasool Allah ﷺ after his Dua(دُعَا),
I am sending you 1000 angels.
Now one Angel would be enough.
We know that Jibril عليه السّلام destroyed the people of loot(لوط) with the tip of his wing.
So, one angel is enough why 1000.
Well, the point here is to give comfort to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
It's not one angel or two Angel,
I mean Allah(عَزّوجَلّ) with  كن فيكون can destroy the entire army.
But here Allahعَزّوجَلّ is giving Tathbeet(تثبيت),
is giving comfort to the Muslims and steadfastness
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ says,
فَلَمْ تَقْتُلُوهُمْ وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ قَتَلَهُمْ ۚ
وَمَا رَمَيْتَ إِذْ رَمَيْتَ وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ رَمَىٰ
وَلِيُبْلِيَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ مِنْهُ بَلَاءً حَسَنًا
إِنَّ اللَّهَ سَمِيعٌ عَلِيمٌ۝
And you did not kill them, but it was Allah, who killed them.
And you threw not O Muhammad(محمد), when you threw but it was Allah, Who threw
that he might test the believers with a good test, indeed Allah is hearing and Knowing.
Now here,
وَمَا رَمَيْتَ إِذْ رَمَيْتَ
You did not throw when you threw but it was Allah, Who threw.
This could apply to any situation of war, where a Muslim is fighting his enemy.
However, the scholars of Tafseer(تفسير) mention a specific incident after which this Ayaah(آية) was revealed.
And that is, they say that Rasool Allahﷺ held in his hand, some sand or dirt,
and he threw it, towards the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and one particle of that sand flew into the face or the eye of every one of the disbelievers.
And that is when Allah(عَزّوجَلّ) revealed this verse,
And you threw not O Muhammad(محمد), when you threw, but it was Allah(عَزّوجَلّ) who threw.
Al-Aswad Al-Makhzoomi(ألأسود ألمخذومي) was an evil, bad character man from the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
He made an oath, he said I'm gonna reach to the wells and drink from them.
And we already said that the wells now were under the control of the Muslims.
So, he marches forth, to go towards the wells
and Hamza رضي الله عنه jumps forth and strikes his leg.
So it came off and Al-Aswad(الاسود) fell on his back
with his leg in the air spurting blood towards the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
But he was so stubborn, he continued crawling in order to fulfill his oath and reach the wells
but Hamza Bin Abdul-Muttalib(حمزه بن عبدالمطلب) struck him again, until he killed him.
Now whether this was the first person to die,
or it was the three men who came out for single combat Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم).
Anyway, Ut'ba Bin Rabiyah(عتبة بن ربيعة)
and his son Al-Waleed Bin Ut'ba(الوليدبن عتبة)
and his brother Shaibah(شيبة), the three of them, stood in front of their army
and challenged the Muslims for single combat, dueling.
Ut'ba(عتبة) and his brother Shaibah(شيبة) and Ut'ba(عتبة)'s son, Al-Waleed(الوليد)
So, the three men are now standing in front of the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and they're facing the Muslims and challenging them for single combat,
Mubaridha(مبارزه), what is called Mubaridha(مبارزه), dueling.
Three young men from among the Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) jumped forth
Auf(عوف) and Muawwiz Ibn Afrah(معوذ إبن أفرع)
and Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبدالله بن رواحة)
And these were all three young men.
When they approached Ut'ba(عتبة),
Ut'ba(عتبة) said: Who are you?
Introduce yourselves.
So, they introduce themselves.
He said: Worthy opponents,
however we want to meet our peers from among our own people.
Ut'ba(عتبة) is saying to these men, that we have no quarrel with you
you know, our problem is not with Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), our problem is not with Al-Aos Wal-Khazraj(ألأوس ولخزرج)
our problem are with the men of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), who followed Muhammadﷺ,
so send us, our peers, people equivalent of our status.
Now, Ut'ba Bin Rabiyah(عتبة بن ربيعة) was one of the leaders of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
he was part of the nobility of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and he comes out with his brother and his son.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) just remember that
a while ago it was Ut'ba(عتبة), who was calling the kuffar(كفار) to go back.
But Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) is the one, who inspired them and fired up, this army to fight
and he cornered Ut'ba(عتبة) by accusing him, of being a coward,
so now Ut'ba(عتبة) is trying to prove that he's not the coward,
and that he's not afraid of meeting the Muslims
because his own son might end up being killed, his son Hudaifah(حديفه)
his stubbornness ended up leading him, to this situation that he was in.
Now Al-Ammawwi(ألأموي), one of the scholars of Seerah(سيرة),
he says that Rasool Allah ﷺ wasn't happy
that three men from among Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار), the ones who responded to the challenge.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted his own relatives, his own family to go out.
So, when Ut'ba(عتبة) send the men back,
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قم يا حمزه' قم يا عبيده'قم يا علي
O Hamza(حمزه), stand up
O Obaidah(عبيدة) stand up,
and O Ali(علي) stand up.
Now, Obaidah(عبيده) here is Obaidah Bin Hariss(عبيدة بن حارث), the cousin of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Obaidah Bin Hariss Bin Abdul Muttalib(عبيدة بن حارث بن عبدالمطلب).
So, he's the direct cousin of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is asking these three men to go forth.
Now, Rasool Allah ﷺ as Al-Ammawwi(ألأموي) says, wasn't happy
because you see, this is the first time, the Muslims and the Mushrikeen(مشركين) are standing face to face in battle.
We had skirmishes before this
but this is the first time, where they would face off each other in single combat.
So by no means, was this an insignificant event.
This was a very significant event.
This Mubaridha(مبارزه) is extremely significant.
In fact, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) says,
I will be the first person who kneels before Allahعَزّوجَلّ, the Almighty among the adversaries on Judgment Day.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) is saying that
I will be the first one to kneel in front of Allahعَزّوجَلّ on the Day of Judgment.
When Allah will judge among Al-Mukhtasimeen(ألمختَصِمين), among the adversaries
among the people who disputed in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
Because these three men from among Al-Mushriqeen(ألمشركين)
and their equivalent, from among Muslimeen(ألمسلمين)
are not facing off and fighting over land,
they're not fighting over wealth,
they're not fighting over power or dominance.
They are fighting over their Lord.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed in Surat Ul-Hajj(سوره الحج)
هَٰذَانِ خَصْمَانِ اخْتَصَمُوا فِي رَبِّهِمْ ۖ
These are two adversaries, who have disputed over their Lord.
And the scholars of Tafseer(تفسير) say, that this Ayaah(آية)
is talking about the Mubaridha(مبارزه), the dueling that happened on the day of Badr(بدر).
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), Hamza(حمزه) and Obaidah(عبيدة)
they rush ahead to face off with Ut'ba(عتبة), Shaibah(شيبة) and Al-Waleed(الوليد).
Obaidah(عبيدة) was the eldest among them, he was the senior, so he faced off with Ut'ba(عتبة),
since Ut'ba(عتبة) was the oldest from among the three Mushrikeen(مشركين)
and Ali(علي) stood in front of Al-Waleed(الوليد).
And These were the two youngest and then Hamza(حمزه) in front of Shaibah(شيبة).
And they started battle, and dust was just erupting from beneath their feet.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and Hamza(حمزه) immediately killed their opponents.
But Ut'ba(عتبة) and Obaidah(عبيدة) both exchanged blows, and both of them fell down,
but they were incapable of carrying on the fight, however, they were not dead.
Each one of them, hurt the other one with a blow
but they couldn't carry on the fight and the same time they were both still alive.
Ali(علي) and Hamza(حمزه) then attacked Ut'ba(عتبة) and killed him and Ali(علي) says,
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not reprimand us for that,
meaning that, it was an acceptable thing to do in a duel.
And then they carried Obaidah(عبيدة) back to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
This was the first Mubaridha(مبارزه) in Islam.
And therefore Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) will be the first to kneel in front of Allahعَزّوجَلّ on the Day of Judgment,
when Allahعَزّوجَلّ will judge among the people, who dispute.
And this could also apply to Hamza(حمزه) and Obaidah(عبيدة).
They carried back Obaidah Bin Hariss(عبيدة بن حارث)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ honored him by placing his head on the thigh of Rasool Allah ﷺ
Abu Talib(ابو طالب), the uncle of Rasool Ullah would say,
we will serve the Messenger of Allah, until we are laid out before him uncaring even, of our sons and our wives.
Abu Talib(ابو طالب) was saying that
we will serve Rasool Allah ﷺ
and we will lay before him our sons, and our wives, and our lives, for him.
Obaidah Bin Hariss رضي الله عنه said, to Rasool Allah ﷺ while he was laying on Rasool Allah ﷺ, on his lap.
He said; O Messenger of Allah, If Abu Talib(ابو طالب) could only see me,
he would know that it wasto me, his words applied.
We will serve him until, we are laid out before him, uncaring even of our sons and our wives.
And this was narrated by Ash-Shafi'e(الشافعي).
Abu Obaidah(ابو عبيدة) was saying that his words really apply to me,
O Messenger of Allah I've laid my life down for you.
And then he passed away.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
اَشْهَدُ اَنَّكَ شَهِيْدْ
I testify that you are a Shaheed(شهيد).
The Ayaat(آيات) from Surat-Ul-Hajj(سورةالحج) that were revealed about the dueling,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says,
هَٰذَانِ خَصْمَانِ اخْتَصَمُوا فِي رَبِّهِمْۖ
فَالَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا قُطِّعَتْ لَهُمْ ثِيَابٌ مِنْنَارٍ يُصَبُّ مِنْ فَوْقِ رُءُوسِهِمُ الْحَمِيمُ۝
يُصْهَرُ بِهِ مَا فِي بُطُونِهِمْ وَالْجُلُودُ۝
وَلَهُمْ مَقَامِعُ مِنْ حَدِيدٍ۝
كُلَّمَا أَرَادُوا أَنْ يَخْرُجُوا مِنْهَا مِنْ غَمٍّ أُعِيدُوا فِيهَا
أُعِيدُوا فِيهَا وَذُوقُوا عَذَابَ الْحَرِيقِ۝
انَّ اللَّهَ يُدْخِلُ الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا وَعَمِلُوا الصَّالِحَاتِ جَنَّاتٍ
جَنَّاتٍ تَجْرِي مِنْ تَحْتِهَا الْأَنْهَارُ يُحَلَّوْنَ فِيهَامِنْ أَسَاوِرَ مِنْ ذَهَبٍ وَلُؤْلُؤًا ۖ
وَلِبَاسُهُمْ فِيهَا حَرِيرٌ۝
وَهُدُوا إِلَى الطَّيِّبِ مِنَ الْقَوْلِ وَهُدُوا إِلَىٰ صِرَاطِ الْحَمِيدِ۝
These are two adversaries,
who have disputed over their Lord.
But those who disbelieved will have cut out for them, garments of fire
poured upon their heads will be scalding water
by which is melted that within their bellies and their skins
and for striking them are masses of iron.
Every time they want to get out of it, from anguish, they will be returned to it.
And it will be said, take the punishment of the burning fire.
Indeed, Allah will admit those who believe
and do righteous deeds to gardens beneath which rivers flow.
They will be adorn therein, with bracelets of gold and Pearl
and their garments therein will be silk.
And they had been guided in worldly life to good speech
and they were guided to the path of the Praiseworthy.
Again these Ayaat(آيات) revealed talking about the single combat
Allah-o-Akbar(الله اكبر), the three Muslims defeated the three Mushrikeen(مشركين) in single combat.
And that is when, the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were enraged
and they started advancing towards the Muslims.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ gave his army instructions,
If they close in, on you then shoot at them,
don't just start firing your arrows haphazardly in a confused state.
Stay calm, control yourself
and when they close in, on you then start shooting them
and then he said and preserve your arrows, and in another narration, gather them.
See, because they were low in ammo.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was telling them, preserve your arrows, don't just fire in every direction in a terrified state.
Wait until, they come close and then start shooting them.
This narration is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
In another narration in Abu Dawood(أبو داؤد), Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
and do not draw out your swords until, they are near to you.
So, continue firing arrows, and then when it's almost hand to hand combat,
that is when you draw out your swords.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), when the battle started
the Mushrikeen(مشركين) started seeing the Muslims as double their number.
You remember, we said that
before battle started the Mushrikeen(مشركين) would see the Muslims, as being less than they really are.
So, they were seeing them as less than 300.
Now when battle started,
suddenly the numbers changed the perception of the size of the Muslim army, changes.
So, the Mushrikeen(مشركين), who are 1000 see the Muslims as being 2000, when they were only 317 or 319.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in Qur'an,
قَدْ كَانَ لَكُمْ آيَةٌ فِي فِئَتَيْنِ الْتَقَتَاۖ
فِئَةٌ تُقَاتِلُ فِي سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ وَأُخْرَىٰ كَافِرَةٌ يَرَوْنَهُمْ مِثْلَيْهِمْ رَأْيَ الْعَيْنِۚ
وَاللَّهُ يُؤَيِّدُ بِنَصْرِهِ مَنْ يَشَاءُ
إِنَّ فِي ذَٰلِكَ لَعِبْرَةً لِأُولِي الْأَبْصَارِ۝
Already there has been for you a sign in the two armies which met,
one fighting in the cause of Allah, and another of disbelievers.
They saw them to be twice their own number by their eyesight.
But Allah supports with His victory, whom He wills.
Indeed, in that is a lesson for those of vision.
So, in the beginning, they see them as less than their own number,
so that they would be careless and they would be willing to fight.
However, when fighting does actually start,
they will see them as double their numbers, so that this will destroy their morale.
And the Muslims had the battle cry, a war cry
and that was Ahad(أحد), Ahad(أحد), Ahad(أحد), Ahad(أحد),
One, One, One, One that was their war cry.
And this was something that the Muslims would employ in their battles,
they would have a certain a fixed war cry that they would keep on repeating.
Harissa رضي الله عنه, one of the Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) was shot by a stray arrow,
so he was killed by friendly fire.
When The battle was over, and his mother met with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
She said;
Tell me whether Harissa(حارثه) is in Paradise, so that I'll be happy
or if he's not, then I'll cry for him.
Rasool told her; Have you gone crazy.
There are plenty ofgardens in Paradise,
and your son has earned the very highest of them.
Your son is in the highest level of Jannah(جنة).
Because Allahعَزّوجَلّ has prepared exclusively for the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) One Hundred levels on top of Al-Jannah(جنة)
and Harissa(حارثه) is in the highest one.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَلَقَدْ نَصَرَكُمُ اللَّهُ بِبَدْرٍ وَأَنْتُمْ أَذِلَّةٌ
فَاتَّقُوا اللَّهَ لَعَلَّكُمْ تَشْكُرُونَ۝
إِذْ تَقُولُ لِلْمُؤْمِنِينَ أَلَنْ يَكْفِيَكُمْ أَنْ يُمِدَّكُمْ رَبُّكُمْ بِثَلَاثَةِ آلَافٍ
بِثَلَاثَةِ آلَافٍ مِنَ الْمَلَائِكَةِ مُنْزَلِينَ۝
بَلَىٰ
إِنْ تَصْبِرُوا وَتَتَّقُوا وَيَأْتُوكُمْ مِنْ فَوْرِهِمْ هَٰذَا
هَٰذَا يُمْدِدْكُمْ رَبُّكُمْ بِخَمْسَةِ آلَافٍ مِنَ الْمَلَائِكَةِ مُسَوِّمِينَ۝
وَمَا جَعَلَهُ اللَّهُ إِلَّا بُشْرَىٰ لَكُمْ وَلِتَطْمَئِنَّ قُلُوبُكُمْ بِهِ
وَمَا النَّصْرُ إِلَّا مِنْ عِنْدِ اللَّهِ الْعَزِيزِ الْحَكِيمِ۝
And already had Allah given you victory at the Battle of Badr(بدر), while you were weak,
meaning few in number, then fear Allah perhaps you will be grateful.
Remember when you said to the believers
is it not sufficient for you that your Lord should reinforce you with 3000 Angels sent down,
previously We said, it was thousand.
So, that was the minimum number Allahعَزّوجَلّ could have sent to them.
But then the number could be 3000 or it could be more like 5000.
And then Allah says; Yes
If you remain patient and conscious of Allah
and they, the enemy come upon you attacking in rage
your Lord will reinforce you with 5000 angels having marks of distinction
and Allah made it not accept as a sign of good tidings for you
and to reassure your hearts thereby.
And victory is not accept from Allah, meaning you don't really need the Angels.
This was a sign of good tidings for you and to reassure your hearts
and victory is not except from Allah, the Exalted in Might, the Wise.
So, in what form did the Angels participate in this battle.
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) himself joined in
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; I saw Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) taking his horse by the reins and leading it.
And all of the angels were wearing white turbans,
except Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل), he was wearing a yellow one to distinguish him.
He was the leader of the army of angels on that day.
In Sahih Muslim(صحيح مسلم),
it says while one of the Muslim warriors was vigorously pursuing one of the unbelievers ahead of him,
He heard above him the noise of a whip striking
and a rider's voice saying:
غِدِّيْ اَبْ هَيْزُوْمْ ، اَقْدِمْ هَيْزُوْمْ
When the Muslim warrior looked at the Polytheist in front of him,
he found him prostrate on the ground.
Examining him more closely, he found that the man's nose has been smashed
and his face split apart by a blow from a whip, all having turned black in color.
So, this was a whip of fire.
The warrior, An Ansaari(انصاري), went and told this, to the Messenger of Allah, Who said;
You speak true that was help from the third heaven.
So, this was an angel riding on a horse called Hayzoom(هيزوم)
And he was saying:
غِدِّيْ اَبْ هَيْزُوْمْ ، اَقْدِمْ، اَقْدِمْ هَيْزُوْمْ
Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) narrates another story, he said;
A Ghafari(غفاري) man said, I and a cousin of mine, were present at Badr(بدر), though we were still Polytheist, then.
So, these were two young men who were Mushrikeen(مشركين),
and they were there just to watch the battle
they wanted to see who would win,
they had no quarrel with either side, they had nothing to do with the battle
they just went there as spectators.
We were up on a mountain waiting for the battle to take place and to see, who would win.
When a cloud approached.
When it drew near the mountain we heard the sound of horses galloping, and a voice saying;
اَقْدِمْ هَيْزُوْمْ ،غِدِّيْ اَبْ هَيْزُوْمْ ،
My companion suffered a heart attack and died on the spot,
while I almost expired, but later recovered.
So, this was quite a shock for these two men, one of them had a heart attack.
Al-Mazini(ألمازني) says;
that while I was pursuing one of the Mushrikeen(مشركين), in front of me suddenly in his head flew off.
So I realized that he was killed by someone other than me.
And they could distinguish the casualties, caused by the angels compared to those caused by the believers.
Anas Ibn Malik(أنس إبن مالك) said;
Our men could differentiate the ones, the angels had killed from those, they had struck by the blow
having occurred above their necks and by their fingertips looking as if they had been burned by a branding iron.
So, the deaths that were caused by the angels, you can know that these were caused by the angels,
first of all, because it was a clean cut
and then because it was black, it was burned, as if it was a branding iron, that was striking them.
Not only did the angels kill but they also captured prisoners of war.
Al-Abbas(العباس) says;
Ya'ani(يعني) when one of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) was dragging Al-Abbas(العباس) and he's saying that he captured him.
Al-Abbas(العباس) said; O Messenger ofAllah, this is not the man, who captured me.
A bald, fine looking man on a pie bald horse,
whom I had not seen with your men, was he, who took me prisoner.
So, The Ansaari(أنصاري) said: No, It was I, who captured him, O Messenger of Allah.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Keep quiet! Allah gave you help of a noble Angel.
Ibn Abbas رضي الله عنهsaid;
the only battle in which the angels participated was at Badr(بدر)
at the other battles, they constituted auxiliaries and reinforcements, that did not actually fight.
The death toll seventy Mushrikeen(مشركين), were killed
and 70 were taken prisoners of war.
Among the Muslims, no prisoners of war whatsoever.
And there were 14 deaths,
Six from among Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون),
six from among Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج),
and two from among Al-Aos(ألأوس).
Some scenes from the battlefield.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf رضي الله عنه, said;
he was flanked by two young men in the rank in the line, in the battle.
He was flanked by two youngmen.
Now, soldiers, know, you want to have good soldiers on your right and on your left.
You want to have good fighting companions, by your side.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) wasn't happy that he has these two kids next to him.
Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن) was a mature man.
And he had these young men next to him.
So he preferred to have someone else flanking him.
And then he said the one to my right.
He whispered to me and said; O uncle show me which one is Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل).
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) said; O, my son, What do you want with Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل).
This young man said;
I swore to Allah, that if I saw him, I would kill him or die in front of him.
Either I kill him or I die right there.
So, now Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمنإبن عوف) is starting to change his mind about who's flanking him.
You know, Don't base your opinion based on the looks.
Don't make a judgment based on the looks.
This man right next to you wants to kill Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل), the leader of the army of Al-Mushrikeen(المشركين).
And then he points out Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) to this young man to his right.
Now the young man to his left
whispers in the ear of Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) and asked him the same question.
And the reason why, they're whispering is.?
These two brothers were competing with each other.
So they were whispering to Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف), so that other one doesn't hear.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) said;
When I showed Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) to them, and he pointed out and he said;
See that man,
you know, it was like a crowd around Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل), all of them protecting him,
so he pointed out Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) and said that's Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل).
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) said, they flew at him like Falcons.
This was in Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ), they flew at him as Falcons, and they struck him down.
They struck Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) down, two young men, from among Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
These two young men, according to one narration are
Muadh Ibn Amr BinJamooh(معاذ إبن عمرو بن الجموح)
and Muawwiz(معوذ) or Auf Bin Afraah(عوف بن أفراح).
And in another narration,
they are two brothers, Auf(عوف) and Muawwiz Bin Ibn Al-Hariss(معوذ بن حارث), whose mother was Afrah(أفراح).
In another narration, it says that when they attacked Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل), and they reached next to him.
One of them struck the foot of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل).
So, it flew off like a kernel of nut would fly off from the Nut cracker.
And it made that sound of a crack and then it flew off.
But then Ikrimah(إكرمه) saw that and he struck Muadh(معاذ) on his shoulder and he tore off his arm.
However, the arm remained, hanging to his body by the flesh of his side, of his chest.
So, the joint itself is tore away, is cut, but the arm is still is just dangling by his side.
And Muadh(معاذ) said: I carried on fighting, dragging my arm behind me,
until it started bothering me and distracting me from fighting,
so I placed it under my foot and stepped over it and tore it off.
That's quite a thing to do.
So, Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) was killed, or was disabled by these two young Ansaari(أنصاري) men.
But he was laying there on the ground on the battlefield, in his last moments.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, asked the Sahabah and said;
who would find out for me, What happened to Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل).
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said: so I went,
and when I realize that the man laying in front of me, was Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل).
I stepped over his neck with my foot.
He said when I recognized him, I put my foot on his neck.
He had once held me captive in Makkah and hurt me and kicked me.
And then he asked him, he said, so Allah has put you to shame then, you enemy of Allah.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) is saying
that Allah has shamed you, you enemyof Allah.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) said;
And how has, He shamed me
Aren't I the most noble man you have ever killed.
Tell me which side won the day?
Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) even though he's in his last moments wants to know the result of this battle.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said; it went to Allah and His messenger.
In another narration, It says that
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبداللهبن مسعود) is saying that
Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) was laying on the ground, holding a fine sword and protecting himself,
while I had the poor sword.
So, I struck his arm so his sword fell off and then I carried his sword.
And I sat on his chest to sever his head, and when I was over his chest.
He said;
لَقَدْاِرْتَقَيْتَ مُرْتَقًا صعْبًا يَا رُوَيعِيَّ الْغَنَمْ
You've climbed very high for having being just a herdsman.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) is arrogant even when he's dying.
He's telling Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) that
for you to be on top of my chest is too high of a place for you.
Because you are but, a herdsmen, you are a Raee(راعي), Ra'al Ghanam(راعي  الغنم).
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said: I then severed his head
and took it to the messengerof Allah ﷺ.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said;
I was as though walking on air,
he was flying in the air, speeding off, Happy, to go and deliver the head of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
I said: this, O Messenger of Allah is the head of Allah's enemy.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
Is it really, By Allah other than whom there is none.
I said: Yes
And then I threw Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل)'s head down in front of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
who then praised Allah(عَزّوجَلّ).
In the narration of Imam Ahmad, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله) Allah has disgraced you, your enemy of Allah.
This man was the Pharaoh of his people.
Every nation has a Firoun(فرعون)
and the Firoun(فرعون) of our nation is Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل).
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) comments on the death of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) and he said;
the death of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) came about at the hands of a youth from Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار)
their after Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) was placed over him.
So, look at who Allah chose to kill Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل),
two young men from Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) and Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود).
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود), who was belittled by Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل)
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود), who was very slightly built.
He was very thin.
One day he was climbing a palm tree and there was wind blowing, and it shook Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود),
he was very light weight.
And the Sahabah laughed when they saw the thinness of the legs of Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said
اَتَضْحَكُوْنَ لِدِقَّة سَاقيه
Are you laughing because he has very slim legs
In the name of Allah, they are heavier on the scale on the Day of Judgment than the mountain of Uhud(احد).
It's not by how pounds you can carry
and how well built you are
and how athletic you are and how powerful and strong you are.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل), the leaderof the enemy's army was killed by Abdullah Bin Masood رضي الله عنه
and by two young men from Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار).
We shouldn't depend on worldly standards.
How strong the soldier is how muscular he is.
A Muslim soldier is supposed to prepare, but not to depend on that preparation, you depend on Allah.
So, Ibn Kathir(إبن كثير) said;
the death of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) came about at the hands of a youth from Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار).
Their after Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) was placed over him,
by this Allah comforted the believers.
And this was more effective than if He had made a bolt of lightning strike Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) down
or made the roof of his house fall upon him
or if he had died a natural death.
And then he recited the Ayah(آية) of Allah
قَاتِلُوهُمْ يُعَذِّبْهُمُ اللَّهُ بِأَيْدِيكُمْ وَيُخْزِهِمْوَيَنْصُرْكُمْ عَلَيْهِمْ وَيَشْفِ صُدُورَ قَوْمٍ مُؤْمِنِينَ۝
وَيُذْهِبْ غَيْظَ قُلُوبِهِمْ ۗ وَيَتُوبُ اللَّهُعَلَىٰ مَنْ يَشَاءُ ۗ وَاللَّهُ عَلِيمٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
Fight them, Allah will punish them by your hands,
not by lightning.
As Ibn Kathir(إبن كثير) says; Dying a natural death.
Allah will punish them, by your hands
and will disgrace them and give you victory over them
and satisfy the breasts of a believing people,
and remove the fury in their hearts
and Allah turns in forgiveness to whom He wills and Allah is Knowing and Wise.
So, there's an element of revenge here because
Muslims have been wronged, they've been oppressed
So, Allah is saying that he will satisfy your breasts
and remove the fury in your hearts.
The Muslims were furious at the Kuffar(كفار)
so Allah will remove that, when they see the faith of the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
One of the famous fighters of Al-Mushrikeen(المشركين)
he was nicknamed, Abul Kirsh(ابو الكرش), the one with the potbelly.
He was covered in armor, you could only see his eyes.
So, Az-Zubair Bin Awwamرضي الله عنه attacked him,
but again this is a man covered in steel from head to toe.
Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(الزبير بن عوام), with his javelins
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), he was able to strike him right in that small opening in the eye.
But the opening was so small, so the spear, the javelin cannot go through.
So, Az-Zubair(الزبير) steps on his Javelin with his foot
and forces it deep into the head of Abul Kirsh(ابو الكرش).
So, when he pulls out his Javelin, the blade was bent, so bad
and this shows you the strength of Az-Zubair Bin Awwam رضي الله عنه,
it was amazing that the blade was bent in such a fashion.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ asked to keep that Javelin as a souvenir
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), when Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away, Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) asked for it.
And when Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) passed away, Umar(عُمَر) asked for it,
and when Umar(عُمَر) pass away, Az-Zubair(الزبير) got it, back again, it was his
but then Uthman(عثمان) asked Az-Zubair(الزبير) to give it to him.
So, Az-Zubair(الزبير) hands it over to the Khalifah(خليفه) Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان).
And when Uthman(عثمان) passes away, Ali(علي) takes it,
and then after Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), Abdullah Bin Zubair(عبدالله بن زبير), the son of Zubair(الزبير), gets it.
Abul-Bukhtari(ابوا لبختري) was one of the noble man of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
He was a Mushrik(مشرك), a disbeliever but he wasn't cruel against the Muslims.
In fact, he was one of the men, who participated in the ending of the siege, against the Muslims.
If you remember in Makkah,
there was a siege that lasted for three years against Bannu Hashim(بنو هاشم) and Bannu Ul-Muttalib(بنوالمطلب),
the family of Rasool Allahﷺ.
Abul Bukhtari(ابولبختري) was one of the men, who ended this siege.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was grateful to him and he asked the Muslims not to kill him, if you see him in battle.
So there's a lesson to learn here
you know that some Mushrikeen(مشركين), even though they are Mushrikeen(مشركين), they are disbelievers
but if they do you good, then reciprocate.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said, If you see him, Don't kill him, leave him.
So, one of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) saw Al-Bukhtari Bin Hishaam(ألبختري بن هشام) and told him
that Rasool Allahﷺ told us not to kill you.
Al-Bukhtari(البختري) said; What about my companion? He had a friend with him.
He said, Well no, we're not going to spare your companion death.
We're going to kill him.
Al-Bukhtari Bin Hisham(ألبختري بن هشام) said;
then I'm going to protect my companion, I'm going to fight to protect him.
And thus, the Ansari(انصاري) was forced to fight Al-Bukhtari(البختري), and he was killed.
Then he went back to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said,
I swear by Him, Who sent you with the truth,
I did try to take him prisoner to bring him to you,
but he insisted on fighting me.
So, I fought back and killed him.
رَبَّنَا آتِنَا فِي الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً وَفِي الْآخِرَةِ حَسَنَةً وَقِنَا عَذَابَ النَّارِ۝
وَصَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته